foreign
2023 and we're in active inference
textbook group slash bookstream
2.02
thanks Ali for joining so what we're
going to do today is give a short
overview of the chapters from the par at
all 2022 book
we're going to do chapters four five
seven
and eight
and we're just going to pause between
them because then we'll clip them into
the shorter videos append that to the
playlist just so there's a first video
overview of each of the chapters and
this is the second in that work
all right so
we'll do
chapter four
um we'll just wait a few seconds and
then start chapter four
okay chapter four is called the
generative models of active inference
and it begins with a quotation
everything should be made as simple as
possible but not simpler by Albert
Einstein Ollie what is your overview
thought or
warning for chapter four
okay so uh after the preliminary
materials
um in chapters two and three uh which
was basically largely based on
um concept providing some conceptual
framework for developing uh the further
Theory chapter four delves into much
more detail in terms of mathematical
formulation and it unpacks a lot more uh
the way that the central equations of
active inference is derived and how to
construct
the important elements of active
inference models uh so say
matrices a b c and d and also how to put
together generative models in different
situations so it basically lays out the
foundation or
um for I mean constructing an active
inference models uh both uh for discrete
time situations and continuous time at
once uh which will be used later in
chapters seven and eight but this is uh
probably one of the most uh challenging
and uh at least mathematically dense
chapters in the book so I would
personally suggest reading through this
chapter really slowly and even if we
don't get to understand every single
detail of the chapter uh obviously we
can return
required as we go through uh the
textbook
thank you Ali yes so let's look through
the sections just to add on though
chapter four is one of the larger and
more equation dense chapters because it
is the common kernel or basis that's
then going to get applied in chapter
five in the neurobiological case
there's a recipe for making chapter 4 in
chapter six that's the recipe for active
inference modeling chapter 7 and 8 are
about the discrete and the continuous
time variant or or subtype or motif of
these kinds of things called generative
models so this is the real common root
and
we'll just look at what the sections are
this chapter complements the preceding
chapters conceptual treatment of active
inference with a more formal treatment
section 4.2 from Bayesian inference to
free energy
what would you say about this section
Ellie
okay so as we know the free energy
principle is inspired by previous work
on Bayesian inference I mean all the way
way back to
helmholtz theory about
um
unconscious inference or something to
that effect I can remember the exact
term but here I mean
it provides in a more in a bit more
detail how we can derive pre-energy
principle uh formalism using the
established Bayesian inference
formulation
and particularly one of the key
uh movements or at least one of the key
decisions uh in uh through the
derivation of free energy principle
formulation is using uh Jane's
inequality principle to derive uh
an upper upper bound instead of just
using uh the exact values to compute
um or or to achieve required parameters
so uh that's basically uh
in my opinion the key premise of uh
section 4.2
and to see uh in a bit more detail how
we can achieve those uh upper bounds
using uh Jane's inequality uh directly
from by using um
I mean manipulations of Bayesian
inference
based in statistical formalism
thanks I'll just add one point from this
section broadly these are the problems
of inferring states of the world
perception and inferring a course of
action planning so this is again
referring to the perception and action
and everything that happens in between
is the internal or the cognitive part of
the inference but this is like the
blanket State cybernetic input output
and then
let's look at the first equation or how
much equations overall or what equations
do you think we should highlight
uh okay so
um maybe we can uh I mean uh just uh as
a general comment about these um
different equations uh well each of
these equations provide a distinct step
toward deriving uh the ultimate whole
picture so uh even if we don't quite
understand how we can derive from uh
each step to the other one
it's good to know that
it's only required to understand how we
get to that ultimate whole picture but
ultimately what we would need in order
to develop
um for a develop active inference models
is the ultimate equation or ultimate
whole picture so this is just
um
a way to elucidate uh the steps toward
developing uh that whole picture but
again it's not an essential requirement
to understand
um the materials of the rest of the book
uh but if we go from uh I mean equations
4.1 toward the 4.4 or other words the
pre A variation of free energy well
equation 4.1 is just a basic definition
of
um probably
some properties of probabilities
in terms of conditional probability and
so on so equation 4.2 provides the
central chains inequality principle and
how it relates to
um I mean conditional probabilities and
uh of course joint probabilities and
then by using uh those uh two properties
or those two equations we ultimately get
to 4.4 which is the definition of
variation free energy parameter uh which
is the parameter of interest that needs
to be optimized in order to inference to
happen
or at least perceptual inference to
happen in active inference models
thanks only thing all add is f is the
letter used for variational free energy
you can think of it like a computer
program and the arguments that it takes
in or the variables that it takes in are
Q which is the distribution that's under
the statisticians control and Y which
are the data which are outside of the
statisticians control
and
do you want to describe more about
anything
in this equation or carry on
uh just one thing to uh that can
probably be helpful is uh to somehow
compare these steps with
um the initial picture we had from uh
chapter two uh because uh variation free
energy was first introduced in chapter
two so uh it can be helpful to go back
and forth between chapters two and four
and try to connect the dots between
um the related points there
section 4.3 generative models
all right I'll read the first sentence
then you can give some thoughts
to calculate the for the free energy
we need three things data a family a
variational distributions and a
generative Model comprising A prior and
a likelihood
in this section we outline two very
general sorts of generative model used
for active inference and the form the
free energy takes in relation to each
but
okay so uh as mentioned earlier
this chapter deals both with discrete
time and continuous time situations so
clearly we would need two different
types of generative models for each
situation and
obviously the the generative models or
the way to construct generative models
or discrete time situations uh would
vary quite a bit from the one for
continuous time situations
um but
the general principle underlying those
General models are basically the same
which is uh I mean to somehow construct
a model of the environment and I mean
either be it
for the situation that that is
sequential in time or for the situations
that need to be somehow
each moment of the situation needs to be
accommodated in terms of a continuous
time situation so uh
figure 4.2 provides some examples of
both so
for uh yes let me see
yes so we have some examples of
different kinds of uh generative models
some uh case case studies if you like
and it provides various ways to show how
the the dependencies between between
variables can be modeled using
these kinds of graphical probabilistic
models so one common way to represent
General to models is to use these kinds
of graphical probabilistic models in
active imprints literature which is at
least in this case the circles would
represent the random variables and the
squares
that would represent the distributions
which would describe
the dependencies between those random
variables
so we can see the clear relationships
between those parameters here which is
basically what this whole graph what
constitutes the generative model that
needs to be used for different
situations and then
in figure 4.3
we can compare
the two different types of generative
models based on uh whether it's discrete
time or continuous time situations so
the upper picture is a generative model
for
the discrete time situation and the
lower picture
is the parallel continuous time version
of it and as we can see the general
topology of these models are the same
the only things that differ is the use
of parameters for
policies or I mean discrete time
policies or the continuous time ones and
we can obviously compare the different
elements for for both uh priors States
and uh external States internal States
and so on by comparing these two models
here
yeah we often return to figure 4.3 it's
kind of the Rosetta Stone
of generative modeling for the context
of this book because it's then going to
develop out into chapter seven and eight
and it represents a really fundamental
decision made in modeling
and
in the later chapters it's also shown
how it can be made into a hierarchical
model that combines aspects of both
but within each level of modeling still
these are the kinds of decisions that
modelers are presented with when it
comes to statistical modeling overall
so section 4.4 goes into essentially the
top half of figure 4.3 discrete time
what would you say about discrete time
okay so uh the discrete time situation
uh is uh obviously the archetype
discrete time situation which is upon
the Palm DP models so at this point I
would very much like to recommend uh
following uh the steps following the
material from step by step paper because
uh that's uh in that paper uh the way to
construct pump DP models is described in
a bit more detail so if anyone feels
like they should learn a bit more about
the the gaps in the details uh I I would
very much like to recommend that
particular paper so
uh yeah uh I don't know how much detail
uh we should go into because uh it's I
mean uh although uh it's not maybe a
detailed enough for some tastes but it
goes in a quite uh extensive detail uh
about how we can construct these models
using the the concepts we've learned uh
in previous chapters uh so
ultimately we reach equations for Point
13 and
4.14 which are basically the culmination
of palm DP formulation using the vector
notations and gradients and so on so
uh
that's when we go to continuous time
situation
great
a few things intervene in the continuous
time
chapter ones that we'll just mention
here because they're kind of boxed or
partitioned from The Continuous time
part about their following Pages first
is Markov blankets we won't go into it
here but kind of footnote that or look
at some other places where we talk about
it outside of this chapter overview
figure 4.4 AZ message passing
again a big topic
let's kind of just go past it now
we're back to the regularly scheduled
continuous time generative model
discussion
and then another box to the generalized
coordinates of motion
so taking position plus derivatives of
precision
and that has some beneficial properties
that are described and unpacked also
elsewhere
do you want to say anything about 4.5.2
uh
uh well the only thing that comes to
mind is
although as I said before
all the formulations here may look uh
more I mean a bit too dense to
understand at the first pass but uh some
of the key uh
maybe components here
could be uh obviously the the material
from box 4.2 and 4.3 uh is I think are
quite essential to understand uh the uh
the underlying principle behind uh
deriving uh The Continuous time
situation because without LaPlace
approximation what we would have uh in
terms of free energy minimization is uh
it would look very much like the Gibbs
it gives free energy so uh I mean the
key distinction between uh
the free energy Principle as described
in active inference literature as
opposed to Gibbs free energy is this
distinction uh is the LaPlace
approximation so this is what enables us
to go from Gibbs free energy to
um I mean uh the variation of free
energy so uh yeah that's uh I mean quite
essential to uh make this to be familiar
with this essential approximation and
obviously the concept of generalized
coordinates of motion will come time and
time again throughout the whole book
particularly in chapters uh eight and
nine uh so yeah those two concepts I
believe
needs a bit more attention
so yeah sounds good box 4.3 LaPlace
approximation
equations
another message passing representation
and a summary
the key message to take away is that
approximate Bayesian inference may be
framed as minimizing a quantity
known as variational free energy this
depends on the generative model that
expresses our belief about how data are
generated anything else you want to add
ah nothing comes to mind at the moment
because uh as I said this is I mean
we're still
in the stage that we want to develop our
essential tools to be used uh in the
rest of the book so uh here up until now
I Believe by the end of chapter four we
have acquired all the essential
necessary mathematical tools and the
next chapter chapter 5 is kind of acts
like an interlude
and I don't think it's the direct
um I mean continuation of chapters uh
one through four so I believe the the
first
um section or the first part of the book
uh conceptually and mathematically ends
here so yeah that's it
yes it's a little bit like the pragmatic
modeling part gets foreshadowed or
explored in five now that we're all
built up with four all right that's the
end of the overview for four
okay chapter five is called message
passing and neurobiology
what is your overview thought on chapter
five
okay uh I mean
uh it's a kind of I don't know I have
mixed feelings about this chapter
because on one hand uh you see as far as
I understand uh active inference uh
although it originated uh as uh
quote-unquote a unified theory of the
brain uh I don't think uh it's a
neurobiological theory per se uh of
course there can be some correlations
between a neurobiological uh components
or concepts with active inference active
inference um I mean Concepts but uh I
mean it's not uh an essential premise of
active inference Theory to provide a
theory to provide a comprehensive theory
about how the neurobiology of human
brain or other organisms brain
behave at it's a detailed and a neuro
anatomical
um level but
at the uh then again it's nice to have
these kinds of empirical correlations uh
between the findings of neurobiology and
the active inference Theory uh but I I
don't think it's uh one of active
inference
um Central assertions at least uh to my
understanding
well said very interesting framing
well chapter five definitely takes a
very specific system of Interest
approach
by highlighting one of the most studied
areas also one of the most relevant
areas which is
mammalian neuroscience
and the chapter is going to introduce a
few different
motifs in the nervous system
and essentially build up towards figure
5.5 which is at the end of the chapter
and 5.5 wires together three specific
neural systems that the chapter is going
to focus on work in that area from
so Ollie said it very well
active inference was built up to in
chapter four
here is another level or type of science
with assertions or with representations
or mappings to any specific system but
this is the kind of modeling that has
been built up and done by fristin power
pizullo and others over the decades with
a focus coming from a human neuroimaging
laboratory setting
a lot of focus and study and attention
and funding and everything on the
mammalian nervous system
but claims about the nervous system have
have uh
are not the basis of what active
inference claims or how it's derived
but this is like an example case study
in neurobiology connecting back to some
of the formalisms that we've just seen
introduced in chapter four
yeah and uh to add a minor Point uh to
what you just said I think it's
important to uh draw attention to the
last sentence of the last paragraph of
the first page it is important to draw a
distinction between a principle I.E the
minimization of free energy and a
process theory about how this principle
may be implemented in a certain kind of
system so I I think uh this sentence
here uh frames this chapter uh in
relation to all the other technical
chapters of this book so if every other
chapter is about developing or at least
up to now was about developing
um
the principled formalism of active
inference now chapter 5 provides a kind
of preliminary sketch for the process
theory of active inference which is uh
obviously far from an extensive Theory
it's just a single chapter but then
again it can provide some important uh
signpost signpost for anyone who wants
to further investigate this area
awesome free energy principle Bayesian
mechanics all things in that area are on
this principle
not responsive to empirical data
and then the process theory is about how
the principle is implemented so the
specific generative models that are made
and how well they map or how well they
do in a portfolio of models that can
have very different goals and
assumptions and all of this
but the process Theory implementation
lets us develop hypotheses that are
answerable to empirical data like
what is the kind of information
or relationship between
photons hitting the retina and
changes in activity in neural systems
and that's an informational question or
can be abstracted in a way to an
informational question that it turns out
does have empirical support and results
in unique explanations and predictions
that doesn't mean that it always results
but a lot of citations are provided here
that's what we can explore in chapter
five
the last paragraph of the first section
describes that they're going to look at
the three different neural systems
okay section 5.2 micro circuits and
messages
what do you think Ali
uh all right so
uh I mean this chapter begins uh from
how a message passing happens in
neurobiological terms
and compare it to the way active
inference frames this message passing
mechanism and specifically if we look at
a figure
5.1 and compare this figure to the ones
we've seen before
in chapters uh in one through four I
think it was in chapter four we can see
some clear parallels between how this
kind of cortical message passaging
happens
in the brain versus how it is framed in
active inference literature and as we
can see it's uh clearly inspired by the
neurobiology of the brain uh but uh then
it's important to keep in mind that it's
not a direct one-to-one mapping between
um these two models uh this is just um a
kind of I don't know
an interesting or
Illuminating uh if you like parallel to
keep in mind uh to somehow be a bit more
confident about the viability of the
theory we want to use for message
passing and active inference uh which is
to say it's not some haphazard Theory
that's just been developed for practical
reasons uh it has some basis in
neurobiology although uh it's not
necessarily fully congruent with every
detail of neurobiological neurobiology
great the specific example is going to
involve this one region of mammalian
cortex tissue that has these six layers
and there's a ton of neurobiology
the big takeaway for figure 5.1 is that
it's possible to graphically lay out
nodes and variables and find some
empirical
correspondences again some unique
explanations and predictions in certain
cases
and that's one kind of modeling where
it's really trying to understand uh and
improve the ability to do correlation
and intervention and counter factual
causal type analysis with the real
system of Interest or in a more
pedagogical setting or in a research
setting or an industrial setting you
might sweep across large families of
structures of models and there's no need
to be grounded to any biological
structure at all
so this is just describing the specific
neural anatomical research that really
arose out of the Imaging work at UCL and
SPM package that's where a lot of this
comes from
5.2 yeah good and sorry just as a side
note uh I think watching uh one of
Thomas parr's lectures on neurobiology
of active inference which is available
in YouTube uh would really help to
understand the materials of this uh
chapter better so I highly recommend
watching that one
thanks
figure 5.2
gives a re-rendering of a kind of
classical View
of a hierarchical predictive coding
system works
so here abstracting a layer from the
tissue
six layer to just two layers here
computational layers now
and then showing how there's
hierarchical communication within a
layer but also
uh well there's they're signaling within
a layer and there's a hierarchy
uh in Bayesian modeling with variables
that are higher order predictions about
other variables and that's the basis of
the predictive coding architecture
so 5.2 looks at some ways that the
something that resonates with the
cerebral cortical architecture enables
what might computationally look like or
have some really strong
and explanatory values in actually
relating to computationally a
hierarchical Bayesian model which could
do various General tasks
all right 5.3 is motor commands leaving
the prefrontal cortex going down to the
butterfly looking cross section here
what is 5.3
okay so 5.3 moves to the other half of
active inference framework which is uh I
mean how how it can model uh the
decision making and ultimately the
movement of the agent uh in order to
minimize the expected free energy as
opposed to variation of free energy that
we saw in perceptual uh half of active
inference
so
it can provide a kind of uh correlation
or analogy between the structural neural
Anatomy uh particularly related to uh I
mean the motor commands and uh
how it can relate to active inference in
particularly The Continuous time active
inference so
we can see that uh for I mean for the
external uh uh event or I'm sorry for
the external State we can take for
example the proprioceptive afferent and
then uh this proprioceptive afferent
acts as a kind of why or the continuous
time active inference which needs to be
uh
um I mean processed in in a way to
optimize the expected free energy and
how it relates to both attention and
precision uh we will see a bit more
detail about uh those uh those terms and
the relation between them in chapter
eight but I think here section 5.3
provides a good summary about the
general uh paths through the motor
command systems of neurobiology
great let's say while the previous case
study focused on how the connectivity
within in between the cortical columns
could have a computational relationship
with a Bayesian hierarchical predictive
coding architecture
the argument of this second case study
is that a continuous input continuous
output
kind of set point seeking
reflexive motor Behavior
with a moving set point with a
descending moving set point enabling
motion by changing ultimately the set
point
and enabling uh variation in the
strategies to reach that set point
through different mechanisms
this is also describable in a compatible
way
that's a shorter section now section 5.4
subcortical structures
what would you say about this section
okay so subcortical
um structures are very important in the
the decision making and and I mean the
planning
of the agents so
uh obviously here we need to uh we need
another kind of analogy between uh the
way
that these plannings and decision
makings happen uh neuroanatomically with
the way uh that uh that it's framed in
active inference but again uh we can see
it's uh clearly based on uh I mean at
least some of the important elements
we've seen from uh the previous chapters
uh so for example we we saw how policy
is described or how how it relates to
outcomes and and preference and so on uh
we can see uh those elements are
directly inspired by a neuroanatomical
structures so
uh
I guess that's uh at least in my opinion
this section here 5.4 uh seems a bit
more uh
sketchy in the meaning that it doesn't
go into quite uh in the extensive
details about how how how those
structures can be
um can be compared about for anyone who
wants to uh
further investigate these topics there
are some useful references put on here
on pages 93 and 94. so
yeah
thanks yeah it's really abbreviated and
overviewed but
we get an interlude from table 5.1
with putative roles of neurotransmitters
so same perspective that we took before
on neural anatomical functionalism here
directly translates to neurotransmitter
reductionism or essentialism or
something like that so certainly all
neurotransmitters and molecules they
play variable roles in different
settings
and
this is the knee in scruffy
manifold all over again
one person might say well we we need a
theory for every acetylcholine molecule
in the world they're all in a unique
context and someone else says all
neurotransmitters are described by one
parameter in this model I'm getting
value from it so to me that's an account
and somewhere in between is the work in
this space which is making an attempt to
have a principled and falsifiable
approach to
model the computational aspects of
specific regions and contexts and
settings and so acetylcholine
noradrenaline dopamine and serotonin are
given a little mini review here
and so it's not an exhaustive or an
exclusive claim it's kind of a
provocation from computational and
molecular neuroscience and people can
look into the papers and also ones that
probably have been published since
5.6 goes to continuous and discrete
hierarchies
which is graphically overviewed in
figure 5.5 so what would you say about
this
uh yeah one interesting thing about this
section is
um
the observation that
our lower level
engagement with the environment uh it
can be most successfully characterized
with continuous time formulations but as
we go up uh on uh I mean on the level of
uh cognitive Concepts or at the level of
cognitive hierarchies and we come to
Concepts such as I don't know decisions
or even beliefs and so on we can reach
the area that the discrete time
situations uh would probably be more
efficient to
to characterize the behavior of the
agent so this multi-scale
[Music]
multi-scale structure of active
inference modeling is quite evident in
the way that our message passing happens
in our brain in terms of our lower level
data processing uh up into
consolidating the higher level cognitive
Concepts and ontologies
awesome thank you
to me figure 5.5 demonstrates the kind
of whole of body approach
that you could imagine there's so many
organs and systems and phenomena for
which there aren't specific generative
models so little can be said about
situations where no generative model has
been articulated and here's one where it
has so it gives you also it's kind of
like reading a drosophila melanogaster
review paper
relatively it's like this is how much
work it takes to get to this state of
knowledge in an insect so then in
another insect do we know less about
that insect empirically and genetically
so consider this to be what's known to
be a lot however also about one of the
most sophisticated or specific cognitive
systems at least we know so there's that
additional kind of like self-reflexive
aspect to this chapter
that is not a Cornerstone of active
inference but here it's just presented
in a synthetic case study
anything else you want to say about five
uh nothing particular comes to mind
all right
okay chapter 7 is called active
inference and discrete time
chapter seven is the first in a pair of
chapters with chapter eight on discrete
and continuous time so that they're kind
of like two forks of a river that we
discussed in chapter four and before and
describe the recipe in chapter six now
seven and eight are kind of like one
level deeper going from the kind of all
of uh this group of animals to one level
deeper into its classification scheme on
the way to the specific generative model
for which it's actually given in its
totality but everything prior to that is
about the learning about its principles
and this is kind of on the trunk of the
path to discrete time modeling just like
chapter eight will be about continuous
time modeling what would you add in
okay so I think uh chapters seven and
eight uh really helps to understand
um in a more practical way uh how the
materials from uh particularly chapters
one through five applies in real time
situations uh so uh even if uh we
somehow didn't get to understand every
details of chapters one through four uh
by when we come to Chapters seven and
eight uh I I think uh I mean some of
those uncertainties uh about or about
our understandings uh can be uh
clarified uh in a in a at least in a
practical sense so uh I believe these
two chapters are really helpful
um in order to consolidate our
understandings from the previous
chapters
awesome well said
so it's going to involve specifying some
discrete time models
7.2 goes into perceptual processing and
the general structure of the chapter is
going to walk through a series of
examples that building complexity
where they first start with perception
in 7.2 introduce decision making and
then describe a few more types of motifs
or cognitive structure or patterns
and also check out step by step and
model stream one where it's built up to
in a different way
so the first example
is I'll let you describe it since it's
Musical
okay so yeah the first example is
um the situation in which we try to
describe the performance of an amateur a
musician in terms of how how we listen
to the performance of an amateur
musicians
in terms of the the predictions we get
from our anticipation of the following
notes as opposed to the actual notes
that's being played so these kinds of
anticipatory reaction uh listening
reaction to the musician can be
successfully formalized using
um discrete time active inference by uh
putting up uh by by
putting together the matrices a uh for
the states and uh Matrix B for the
transition between the states
um or the transition probabilities which
uh describe in this case describes uh
the probability from going from one note
to the other and uh obviously the
um the actual sequence that's been
played which can be described with uh
The Matrix T so uh and another Point uh
I wanted to point I wanted to mention is
for anyone who has downloaded this
chapter uh before I don't know I think
about June or something
I recommend re-downloading it from mit's
website because uh they have corrected
some of the typos that was previously
present in this chapter particularly in
gear 7.2
cool so this graphical model
where a person is listening this is a
general perceptual Bayesian framing it's
specified
just like with any other equations
there's a lot to look into but a
indicates the probability of an outcome
given a state
this is saying if it were all
on the diagonal like an identity Matrix
this is kind of a common Motif then
States kind of map to themself so in the
context of
uh
uh in the context of this model A
represents the mapping between the
observed note and the underlying hidden
true note
FNB describes the transition Matrix of
how those change to time D is the prior
they're specified
figure 7.2
you want to describe it
foreign
so in figure 7.2 or at least the
incomplete version of uh figure 7.2 we
see here uh well at the upper left uh
part of the picture uh we see uh I mean
uh the beliefs about uh about each note
uh at each step at each time step and at
up upper right uh we somehow translate
those uh beliefs into a specific
numerical values uh so uh so instead of
just
assigning some continuous values we uh
we we've simplified the situation by
assigning some discrete numerical values
for each note and then
the lower left is supposed to show the
uh the act the free energy gradients and
over time uh or in in other terms uh the
prediction errors uh we get from
um I mean
comparing our predictions with the
actual outcomes uh so lastly uh lower
right picture uh shows uh in parallel to
the upper right picture uh determines uh
the values of these errors so uh we we
can see both
uh the The Continuous the initial or at
least initial uh continuous assignments
and values and then the further uh
discretizing of the values in order to
get the discrete time situation or the
more tractable at this group time
situations
okay
so it's a general passive inference task
where there's priors about how states
are going to change through time and
then there's real data coming in so
that's the kind of classical predictive
coding video compression common filter
Bayesian setting
7.3 introduces a key Motif which is
decision making and planning as
inference so this is the idea of having
a base graph where the variables can
relate to different things there's high
composability and here the idea is that
a variable is going to be proposed that
we can do inference about that describes
the process of decision making or policy
selection so what would you say about
7.3
okay so 7.3 is
obviously similar to what we saw in
chapter 4 and if I'm not mistaken even
the topology is exactly the same with
that picture we saw previously so uh
yeah this is the initial setup to or
which acts also as a review
about how these different
components of General upon DP General to
models needs to be
described in in such situations but uh
ultimately the specific case study we
come across in this section is uh
the attempt to model uh the behavior of
uh of a of the mouse in a teammate so
rat and a teammate so
um especially uh teammates containing uh
an aversive stimulus in one arm and an
attractive stimulus on the other so this
is this can act as a kind of toy example
to use uh this kind of probabilistic
modeling to uh
describe these situations
thanks so that leads us right to figure
7.4 here's a visualization of the
situation with the the rat in this case
where there's a a pleasant and aversive
stimuli
on each end of a decision point
and there's also a epistemic opportunity
to receive some information about the
context that the animal is in
and so that setting is described for
both the case with white on the left
block on the right and block on the left
white on the right
and those are shown in terms of their
differences in the matrices the explicit
specification of the generative model
visualizations show some of the slices
of the B variable
which reflect different transition
probabilities
C represents the preferences which are
expressed over the observable States
D reflects the priors on the different
states that need priors
7.4 what would you say about this
yeah okay so in 7.4 it builds up on the
previous section and adds other elements
that we previously saw in chapters three
and sorry two and four uh which is how
the exact formulation for
um
expected free energy can be used sorry
variation free energy can be used to
formulate the trade-off between uh the
uh I mean information uh seeking and and
or at least uh between the epistemic
value and information seeking so uh here
it uses uh again that rad example in a
bit more uh more extended and elaborate
form to formulate the epistemic value of
observing a q in a given a given
location
and figure 7.7 is a representation of
this situation
but another situation that's been
uh let me see yeah in 7.9 another case
study discussed here is uh is is the
situation of uh The Psychotic eye
movements and um because it is something
that can be quite successful you just
describe or characterize in terms of
information seeking versus the epistemic
value and the situation here is
uh let me see yeah
shown visually in figure 7.9 which
clearly shows how our visual uh
psychotic eye movement eye movements can
be
um
described in such a way as to as to kind
of trace the trajectory uh of our eye
movement among different regions of the
visual space so
uh and how the information We Gather
from a given region can be can affect
the
um I mean the subsequent trajectories of
our psychotic eye movements so
um
yeah that's basically
the main premise of
this section I guess
nice great
7.5
what would you say about it
okay so uh 7.5
again adds another dimension uh to the
previous formulations and this time we
get to update the generator models by
learning and the
um
so the the generative models for this
situation is a bit more complicated than
the previous ones because it now needs
to account for a mechanism or a way to
update the matrices we had before so in
the previous situations uh we we didn't
account for learning per se but here
we directly update our general sorry
the word update can be confusing here we
we get to somehow
improve our generative models to
accommodate for these
updating accounts and
yeah so uh this the situation here uh or
the case of study uh uh here uh which uh
somehow elucidate the way that the
learning
um can be a common can be accounted for
with these models is uh
again a toy example of a creature uh in
a in a simple world of uh
black and white tiles which kind of
tries to find a a path to reach a given
destination a certain destination
so it is more complicated than the
situation we had for the rat example
because it only had
um I mean simple trajectories that
needed to
um
a Traverse but here uh the creature or
the agent in this case needs to do lots
of a lot more learning and information
seeking and so on so all the previous
elements uh is kind of combined in this
example and it's a really good example
to see how the different components of
active imprints can be
connected to each other
nice
and seven six hierarchical or deep
inference
first a box 7.3 interlude on structure
learning boxed off topic and a lot to
say but structure learning broadly
refers to learning the structure about a
model
using the same types of methods that you
might to do inference on for example a
more observable
sensor data reading something like that
this section Works towards the idea of
nested inference or or multi-scale
modeling
what would you say about figure 712
so again this situation
is um I think the most complex
situations of this chapter which builds
up uh from the previous sections uh and
this time it adds another layer to
accommodate for
for the inferences that happen uh in uh
I mean different time steps so in this
case we have multi-time or multi-scale
inference and learning happening
um both at the levels of
um sorry at the levels of learning and
at the levels of information seeking so
this
this is represented in
figure
7.12 which represents how uh kind of
this fractal generative model can be
seen as a component in um
this multi-scale bigger generative or
and as a kind of leaf in this bigger
bigger generative model uh so it can be
seen as a lower uh level inference
happening at the leaf level going up to
the hierarchy and influencing sorry uh
collaborating on the whole process of
learning and inference at the higher
level so
um
yeah yeah I guess that's
somehow summarizes this figure so if you
have anything to add
that's that's great
it's an example of the composability
of generative models
what
we've uh talked about and had Toby
Sinclair Smith describe as as the
compositional cognitive cartography
and just what kinds of connectors can
and can't you do and how can that Motif
that the discrete time model introduces
and then the rest of these features
including action and learning and so on
get layered in on top what can you do
with that
713 gives another example
do you want to say anything about it or
maybe continue on uh yeah so the case
study here is the example of
um linguistic I mean language learning
uh through reading so not language
learning uh maybe it's just what happens
uh sometimes
yeah yeah in comprehension so what
happens when reading and
in a anticipatory way uh the the words
that that comes each after the other so
uh why this kind of situation uh can be
most successfully characterized with
this kind of modeling because it
involves a different scales of learning
and comprehension both at the level of
I mean reading at the level of uh
somehow observing the letters and then
going onto uh the words and then word
groups and so on uh so uh yeah that's uh
really interesting way to uh again
combine all of those elements uh into a
single unified model to see how those
different time scales slow and fast time
scales
operate together to
to build this more encompassing model of
more incoming generative model of the
situation
pray any closing thoughts on seven
uh nothing particular now thanks
all right
next chapters chapter eight which is
going to go into the continuous time
all right chapter 8 is called active
inference and continuous time begins
with that Timeless quote everything
flows nothing stands still
what would you say about chapter eight
all right so this chapter uh probably is
at my most favorite chapter in the book
uh because of my own personal interests
in
um uh I don't know the process
materialism and so on but uh yeah so
chapter seven
um
and acts as a really good starting point
for anyone who wants to
develop the discrete time situations and
to model the screen time situations uh
enacted within active inference
framework but in chapter 8 we kind of
get into get to
a Model A bit more interesting or let's
say more involving situations uh and
they're not necessarily
a kind of toy examples we saw at least
at the beginning of chapter seven
so
obviously as the title suggests this
chapter deals with the continuous time
situation so uh in the in that case
we'll need to
and maybe at this point refresh our
memory about what continuous time
situation involves by reading the
relevant Parts reading Arabian relevant
parts of chapter four so
uh yeah in chapter four we saw that the
generative model for continuous time
situation uh derives derives from uh the
uh it was a stochastic calculus in terms
of uh putting the whole process
um into two elements uh two stochastic
um two elements of stochastic equations
uh one of which is the actual uh State
and the condition of actual States
um or the behavior of the actual States
and the other one uh is the randomness
that we need to account for in each
real-time continuous time situations so
that's what we get here in equation
eight a 8.1 and then building up from
that equation uh we
um it generalizes that equation to
involve uh I mean
the fun the functionals of G and F
instead of just
um the
um
the single valued functions of G and F
so uh then we get to
put that into uh the situation that can
be used for describing the behavior of
dynamical systems which is a very well
known uh situation to use these kinds of
uh stochastic equations and it's widely
studied how those those kinds of
Dynamics can be characterized especially
in recent Bayesian mechanics paper by
Dalton exactly vadavel and others so
and then it gets to some more specific
examples such as a lockable terror
Dynamics and the synchronicity and so on
in order to show how these kinds of
Dynamics can be
elaborated upon and can be generalized
to
and and enables them to characterize a
more complex situations so
uh
get that's a really short and brief
overview of the whole uh chapter maybe
uh we can talk about a bit more details
as we go through
right well said well I'm sure for
another day the philosophical
implications of a seven and eight and
high road and low road and all these
other parts of the textbook great topics
um I I agree I would see chapter 8 as
demonstrating continuity
with some classical
continuous time modeling motifs from a
few different areas of dynamical Systems
Science which is applied in like many
many many fields but these are some
classical examples so figure 8.1 goes a
little bit more into depth or at least
into more formalism detail about exactly
what we saw in chapter five with the
spinal reflex arc with the
proprioceptive data coming in and then a
differential being calculated with the
set point which reflects a descending
prediction from a decision-making layer
and that can be viewed as this kind of
mechanics that plays out in a phase
space in continuous time like a spring
moving around with with someone making a
certain path with an attractor and a
spring being dragged around something in
that area
box 8.1 goes into a very fascinating
topic do you want to describe it
uh well uh it's uh maybe uh one of the
most
um thought-provoking uh section pages of
the whole book and if I remember
correctly uh in all of the cohorts this
particular box
I mean gives always gives rise to lots
of questions uh because of some of the
interesting and uh at least initially
counter-intuitive
claims here
but I don't want to spoil it so
um
but as a kind of spoiler alert it kind
of
gets to a really interesting but uh alas
very brief discussion about the
comparing these terms Precision
attention and sensory attenuate and the
relation and similarities and difference
between these two these three terms and
how each understanding each of them is
essential to understanding the other
ones but
as I said it's a really interesting
topic which gives rise to lots of
discussions
and I believe it's one of those
topics that uh that's worth looking a
bit more uh looking into in some other
literature as well
great well said what a cliffhanger
next they go to a classic Model family
called lockabletera
these Dynamics inherit from
characterizations of Predator prey
Dynamics in ecology
so it's kind of a classical ecology
model shown in figure 8.2 on the top
it's actually the ecosystem model plants
herbivores and carnivores which follow
different kinds of oscillatory Trends in
continuous time
and so that also has enabled it to be
applied for other so-called winnerless
competitions and that relates to topics
like neural Darwinism and also
neurodynamics where things have kind of
oscillatory relationships with each
other which are being modeled as a
continuous time underlying process
with a lot of measurement noise and
discretization through space and time
but those are the kinds of algorithms
that SPM explores more and there's lack
of Volterra and a lot of other dynamical
systems theory in SPM
so active inference kind of adds action
and more to what was laid out from a
pure dynamical systems theory in SPM
here it really is just showing the
ecology example and how you can project
if you have three different species you
can think about that motion in a cube or
tetrahedron and then you could project
onto kind of like looking at a lower
dimensional manifold relating just two
of the three species
and that events is this kind of
oscillatory but also moving Behavior
that gets connected in figure 8.3 to
neurobiology what would you say about
this
uh okay so here in figure 8.3 uh we see
some applications of
um a lock of Altera Dynamics uh so uh
the left column uh here uh show
represents
um what happens in I mean in eye
blinking eye blink conditioning so uh of
course here we need to account for
uh I mean the expected States
of uh of the of the sequel of the
sequences of events that happens in in
the eye blinking so uh the upper
upper left figure shows the expectations
uh in terms of time and then
uh the parallel right hand side equation
sorry right hand side figures uh shows
the uh
the lock of Altera system that that is
applied
um in the handwriting situation so as we
can see although uh the uh I mean
mathematical technology is the same or
at least the modeling technology is the
same
the outcome of each situation uh varies
drastically in
two distinct
um
the two distinct neurobiological
Behavior not neurobiological but
biological Behavior Uh so yeah we can
see how the same modeling framework can
give rise to
different
outcomes uh based on what parameters is
needs to be optimized what parameters
are selected for the modeling and so on
so I believe it's quite
uh interesting example to compare
handwriting and the blinking together
and how those can be compared to each
other using the last couple Terror
Dynamics
great thank you
box 8.2 gives a variance on the learning
here presented with the formalism for
continuous models kind of a technical
aside
section 8.4 is about generalized
synchrony so figure 8.4 is going to
visualize one of the classic dynamical
systems which is the Lorenz attractor so
what would you say about this
bigger okay so this section is uh truly
interesting because uh
when one thinks of active inference
probably the first situations that comes
to mind is uh the situations in which we
have a quite well-defined uh probability
distributions for different parameters
but as we can see here in
section 8.4 actually some of the
formalism of active inference can be
successfully used to characterize even
chaotic systems and partic and in
particular the way in which two chaotic
systems can be synchronized with each
other so this is a classic example of a
chaotic Lorenz system
and it derives from it draws upon from
some of Professor person's earlier work
on Birdsong synchrony
and as a side note any literature before
2016 is considered earlier history in
active inference literature because it
evolves uh quite rapidly so
uh yeah this kind of synchrony between
two chaotic systems uh can be
interpreted as providing evidence or
even
let's say a way to model a kind of
primitive theory of mind uh in in the
sense that how exactly can we
understand uh or can two two agents can
trace each other's trajectories uh
without
um any I mean engaging in any direct
exchange of observations between their
internal and external States so uh yeah
that's a really good example and I
believe one of the most interesting
examples of how active inference can
even account for these kinds of uh
Behavior so
and the rest of the section goes into
the details of how this kind of
synchrony between
um multi multi-scale uh Birds
multi-scale Lorenz systems can happen
um and how can we
formulate it mathematically in terms of
continuous time active inference
awesome and there's been more recent
work on Mark all blankets and stochastic
chaos but the bird example is a classic
8.5 goes into hybrid discrete and
continuous models so this could be kind
of like a in-between chapter of seven
and eight but now that we've been
introduced to the pure form of discrete
in the pure form of continuous models
here shown the dot composability extends
to so-called Hybrid models where here
the lower level visually is using the
continuous time formalism
and the higher level is describing the
little line added here the discrete time
formalism and this was the similar
structure described by the authors of
the paper octave inference does not
contradict folk psychology
where they describe this lower level as
motor active inference which was closely
allied with the spinal Arc reflex shown
above and then this higher level they
call decision active inference because
in that case it was referring to a
discrete decision
and so they used that kind of basic
motif of continuous activity or
continuous time modeling at the more
peripheral aspects of a cognitive entity
and like Ali said more discretization
[Music]
and hybridization as well at higher
levels of the cognitive modeling
and that type of an architecture here
instead of describing who wants the ice
cream cone I believe
here it's gonna be a mixed or hybrid
model that is going to call back the
isocade
system
where there's a fixed point
that is able to be moved as a set point
and then there's a continuous time
isocade that pursues the new fixed point
and so that's analogous to a new set
point or fixed point being specified
from the top down muscle command about a
new location for a muscle followed by
movement towards it this is a muscular
activity that is realizing that but but
not in the elbow coming away from the
hot stove this is about the eye cicading
to an epistemic foraging location
specified by top down hierarchical
systems
8.3 describes little technical aside on
mixture of gaussian gaussian mixture
models kind of a
technical modeling note an 8.6 closes
it says it's a huge topic and much has
been left out and so they list in table
8.1 key advances in continuous time
models and those areas are
synthetic bird song
ocular motor delays
conditioned reflexes smooth Pursuit eye
movements psychosis illusions cicades
action observation attention Hybrid
models and self-organization
and that's chapter 8. what else would
you say and also what would you kind of
lead someone to in the philosophical
implications of eight because it sounds
kind of cool
uh okay so
uh well uh the case of continuous time
active inference uh
uh
I think it leads to
a really interesting questions uh both
in terms of uh philosophical questions
and also uh a more practical modeling
questions about uh what parameters needs
to be accounted for and so on uh and as
I said I believe it's a more and more
interesting way of
um if not interesting but but at least
more involved way of doing active
inference modeling but uh one thing that
uh one of the philosophical questions
that
when I uh have explored in our paper is
how
the processes of I mean ontological
processes can
uh philosophically described using fpp
assertions in terms of their interaction
with the environment
[Applause]
in which they co-constitute themselves
and we don't necessarily
distinguish between uh between the
internal and the external state so one
obvious example of this is that
generalized synchrony example that we
saw in this chapter in which we don't
necessarily distinguish between which of
the birds act as
the agents and which one is the um
environment or device versa so these
kind of co-constitution of the
environment and the agent which gives
rise to the partitioning of State space
through a markup blanket is uh one of
the interesting uh
philosophical points that I think needs
to be elaborated
a bit more using and some of the recent
advances in philosophy such as the two
the tools that's been developed in new
materialism
school or some other philosophical
approach approaches but yeah these kinds
of uh what exactly gives size gives rise
to emergence what is the ontological
status of emergent properties and so on
are some of the
um
burning questions for many philosophers
today and I believe active inference in
particularly continuous time active
inference provides a clear uh precise
mathematical formalism uh even if not to
answer these questions but at least to
explore it in a more rigorous and uh
practical way and also
practical and attractive attractable way
so this is the area that I believe uh
philosophy and science uh are
beautifully intertwined uh into a
coherent view of not only
the phenomenon of interest but even
about the whole world
wow
wow pretty cool yeah a lot to say about
that topic
after completing chapter seven and eight
you've seen the kind of two major
branches or two major motifs of just one
kind of modeling but these kind of
models have so many different forms that
that's why it's such a Hands-On process
to specify the generative model in
chapter six and fit it with data in
chapter nine those are all what's
required and that's kind of the last
mile of where these discussions about
General motifs gets you
but also playing with these pedagogical
models can be really helpful because it
will help you understand the basic
patterns and relationships and start to
see see different patterns in the
graphical models and know from there
what levels of technical processes can
be kind of coarse grained over
all right
okay well that's it
um I guess next time we will do probably
9 10 and maybe something else
all right I'll end it now thanks Holly
thank you